Guide to the Thomas Swain Barclay Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Thomas Swain Barclay papers
1915-1984
SC0327
Barclay, Thomas S. (Thomas Swain), 1892-1993
9 Linear feet
Correspondence, ephemera, photographs and scrapbooks relating to the American political process, student government at Stanford, and his teaching activities. Includes some correspondence from James Farley.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Political scientist. Professor of political science at Stanford University from 1927 until his retirement as emeritus in 1958, Barclay also served on the U.S. State Department's Peace Commission after World War I. In his active political life, he served for 18 years as a member of national and state Democratic Party committees, as a delegate (1936 Democratic National Convention), as a presidential elector (1944), and as assistant to Democratic Party chairman James Farley (1940).
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, ephemera, photographs and scrapbooks relating to the American political process, student government at Stanford, and his teaching activities. Includes some correspondence from James Farley.
Access Terms
Barclay, Thomas S. (Thomas Swain), 1892-1993; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976; Stanford University. Department of Political Science. Faculty.; Democratic Party--California.; Students--Political activity.; United States--Politics and government.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Papers on American Academics and Politics, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on Constitutional Issues; ads for Lectures, 1927-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Remarks by Pres-elect Ronald Reagan; Articles on Supreme Court; FDR, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Julia Darcy Scott, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pics of Julia D'arcy Scott; wedding invites; articles, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles of Humor, Satire -- Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles on Pres. Pitzer; paper on Library, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Paper on Political Situation of Nixon; photo of Barday, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles on Politics; some satire, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Papers on conferences; correspondece; political reports, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wedding invites; newspaper clippings; correspondence from Columbia University, 1938-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wedding Invites; political satire; correspondence from Farley/Wilbur, 1936-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Paper topics for Government class; paper on war; clippings, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photos from Childhood; papers on geneology; records of family marriages and deaths (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippinsg on books and Polisci; notes on political sources, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence; political clippings; obituary for Rossiter Johnson--Sierra Camp Article, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Articles on Politics; correspondence from J. Farley; obituaries fpr G. Lefevre; clippings on teaching speech transcript, 1923-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Political Party Reports; Stanford Ma 1977; Correspondence to S. from T. Barclay, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Democratic Party Papers; photos and articles on teaching; papers on Tom Barclay Scholarship, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Enrollment Cards; correspondence; clippings on polisci issues; commencement Miss U 1916; clippings on academics, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Missouri Commencement book--papers and photos from fraternity beta theta pi, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Article on Teachers; correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Paper on T. Roosevelt, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Book of Political Cartoons, 1913-1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence; articles on teaching and schools; clippings on books; polisci articles, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Recepits and Bills; certificates from Democratic Party; correspondence-1980s; common cause magazine; jr. high diploma, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Recepients of IR awards; correspondence to S From T. Barclay, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Polisci articles; correspondenec; polisic papers, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence; articles on polisci issues, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Papers on AT&T Shares, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Papers on poli sci issues; commencement of Miss U 1962, 1931-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Papers on poli sci; centennial for Miss U; Papers on Howard L. McBain, 1922-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Articles on Barclay; correspondence from J. Farley and others, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from J. Farley - 1940s; IR and poli sci papers; correspondence and wedding invites; correspondence from H. Hoover; photos; blank stationary, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence; papers and articles on teachers and honor awards; reunion pictures and papers; ads for conferences; frat. Alum news; articles on Barclay; b-day cards; photos of grandchildren, 1957-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Poli sci papers and topics and exams, 1933-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notes on poli sci issues by Charles Beard, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Articles on poli sci and school issues; blank postcards; correspondence from 1970s, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bureaucratic info on Stanford 1941; frat. reunions; clipping on Columbia University; blank stationary, 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Articles; papers and class notes on poli sci issues, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Transcripts of speeches at a dinner in 1941; correspondence 1939-1942; graduation address from Cornell; Centennial pamphlet from Miss U (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - pictures, postcards; euology for George Lefevre: tribute to Thomas Jefferson; pamphleton School of PoliSci at Columbia, 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes & correspondence from the Social Science group, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - info on the John H. Watrous fund; invites to fraternity functions: holiday greeting cards, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - PoliSci paper on Charles A. Beard; Pacific Historical Review - 1936; personal clippings; correspondence; photos & post-cards; clippings on Dr Lefevre (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence on having received honorary degree from MissU, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence honoring him on his Retirement, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - His speech at Retirement: more correspondence on his Retirement, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Humorous stories: clippings on academic issues; correspondence, 1923-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Report on prohibition, photos of T. Barclay: correspondence from mother & others 1918-1919: papers on Amer. in post WWI in Europe (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Blank stationary, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1977: academic articles, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Inst. paper on Latin Amer. Sri Lanka, & organized labor, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Paper by Neil Cotter on Eisenhower, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Certificate for being an elector from CA for 1944 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1972 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on PoliSci & personal issues greeting cards; correspondence also from James Farley, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Directory for Phi Beta Kappa; clippings on Political & Teaching issues: humorous stories; correspondence, 1951-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on students & school: humourous stories or sayings, 1968-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Clippings about T. Barclay and correspondence, 1941-1957 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Corresponence 1917-199; WWI & PoliSci clippings humorous sayings, 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - PoliSci articles & personal correspondence from James Farley & other - 1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Prints of Stanford scenes (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - News clippings, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Humorous sayings: clippings on PoliSci issues or teaching: Phi Beta Kappa invites: correspondence: football clippings, 1951-1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photos; clippings on Barclay; papers on Phi Beta Kappa; correspondence; political clippings, 1928-1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photos; correspondence and invites, 1946; political papers and clippings; humorous sayings (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, James Farley and others; political articles; invites from Betas and articles on Phi Beta Kappa; humorous anecdotes, 1947-1950 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Football memorabilia; political articles, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Humorous sayings; Phi Beta Kappa articles and political science articles; wedding invites; correspondence from James Farley and others; photos, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Phi Beta Kappa articles; humorous sayings and anecdotes; photos; correspondence; articles on politics; wedding invites, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence; articles on politics; photos; wedding invites; humorous sayings; fraternity reunions, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Political articles; Phi Beta Kappa articles; wedding invites; humorous sayings; correspondence; photos, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Wedding invites; Phi Beta Kappa articles; articles on politics; correspondence from J. Farley and others; humorous articles; photos, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Articles on politics and Phi Beta Kappa; correspondence; humorous stories and sayings; wedding invites; photos, 1954-1956 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - School events; invites; articles on politics and Phi Beta Kappa; photos; correspondence; humorous sayings, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Wedding invites; clippings on politics, education, Phi Beta Kappa; humorous stories; correspondence; photos of FDR, 1944-1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on politics; humorous sayings; photos; invites; correspondence from J. Farley and others; Phi Beta Kappa; blank stationary, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Articles on school, politics; humorous stories; invites; photos; Phi Beta Kappa, 1944-1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Humorous sayings and anecdotes; correspondence; Phi Beta Kappa; political science, football, and Stanford-related articles; wedding announcements and invites; photos, 1944-1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Humorous articles and sayings; correspondence from J. Farley and others; poli sci and Stanford articles; wedding invites, 1944-1945 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Stanford-related and poli sci articles; humorous articles; correspondence; photos; Phi Beta Kappa, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Wedding invites and announcements; humorous articles and sayings; photos; Phi Beta Kappa; articles on teaching, school, poli sci and football; correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence; wedding invites; Beta fraternity; poli sci and school related articles; football articles; photos, 1927-1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Photos; poli sci articles; wedding invites; correspondence; Phi Beta Kappa; humorous anecdotes; Beta fraternity; football articles, 1933-1937 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Humorous stories and sayings; correspondence; Ike as president of Columbia U; photos; Phi Beta Kappa, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa; humorous stories and sayings; correspondence; wedding invites; poli sci articles; photos, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - PoliSci articles; school-related topics; photos; humorous stories and sayings; football articles; wedding invites; Beta fraternity, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Humorous stories and sayings; clipping on Stanford-related events; Poli sci; betas; photos; wedding invites; correspondence; personal clippings, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Greeting cards; correspondence from father and others; papers from his father's hardware co., 1911-1952 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Wedding invites and various other announcements, 1943-1947 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Democratic party pamphlet, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - PoliSci articles; clippings on Barclay; football papers; wedding invites; Stanford-related papers; honoring Dean Ford, 1930-1938 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Photos; football memorabilia; Poli Sci articles; wedding announcements and invites; personal clippings, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Personal clippings and on Poli Sci; Phi Beta Kappa; photo ID; humor; photo; invites; correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Football articles; Memorial paper commemorating 100 years of Joseph Pulitzer, 1927, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Invites; poli sci and personal clippings; humor; correspondence; football articles; photos, 1947-1948 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Poli sci and personal clippings; Stanford-related articles, 1944-1945 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Humorous stories; football; personal info and clippings; Phi Beta Kappa; correspondence; greeting cards; photos; invites, 1936-1938 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Invites; personal info clippings; humor; photos; Stanford and teaching articles; correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Poli sci articles; humor; photos; correspondence; invites, 1937-1975 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Clippings; notes; photos; humorous stories; correspondence; greeting cards, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence; clippings; humorous stories; greeting cards, 1935-1937 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Poli sci and humorous clippings; football; school articles; party politics; correspondence; personal interest clippings; wedding invites, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence; personal interes clippings; photos; teaching forums; humor and poli sci clippings; Phi Beta Kappa, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Wedding invites; correspondence; humor and poli sci clippings; photos; ads for teaching conferences; personal interest clippings; Phi Beta Kappa, 1940-1943 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Teaching; humor articles; wedding invites; football; correspondence, 1940-1956 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Humor; football; teaching and Stanford clippings; photos; correspondence; Betas, poli sci articles, 1928-1931 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence; poli sci; humor and teaching clippings; wedding invites; Phi Beta Kappa; personal interest clippings; Betas, 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Political science papers, 1911-1920 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Newspapers on his retirement, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Album of baseball photographs and news clippings, 1909 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - California Senate Resolution, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Album of letters honoring Barclay upon his retirement, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - News clippings, photographs, and fraternity memorabilia, 1911-1912 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-1991-079
  - Certificate of appreciation to Barclay from U.S. Senate, signed by Frank Church, Lee Metcalf, Mark O. Hatfield, and Alan Cranston; on the occasion of the fiftieth anniversary of the Department of Political Science, 1970 (Box 1)
    OS item boxed with assorted SC oversize materials:
  - Papers on American Academics and Politics; Report on Fundraising; Oral History by Dr. Barclay, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings on Constitutional Issues; ads for lectures; reports and editorials on academic issues, 1927-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Remarks by Pres-elect Ronald Reagan; articles on Supreme Court; FDR; Report on Hoover Institution, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Julia D'arcy Scott; Political Science Papers and Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pic. of Julia D'arcy Scott; wedding invites; articles on Poli Sci issues; random funny quotes and anecdotes; blank stationary from Cornell, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles of humor and satire; correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article on President Kenneth Pitzer; papers on library, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Paper on political situation of Nixon; photo of Barclay, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles on politics; some satire, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Papers on conferences; trips; article on Julia D'arcy; marriage invites; correspondence; papers on Alien board; political reports, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wedding invites; newspaper clippings on Barclay and political topics; some correspondence from Columbia University, 1938-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wedding Invites; political Satire; correspondence from James Farley (democratic national committee), Ray Wilbur; ads for political Forums, 1936-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Paper topics for Government 106; paper on war; clippings on political science and the democratic party, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photos from childhood; papers on geneology; records of family marriages and deaths (Box 1, Folder 14)